LUNCH BREAK
（午休时间）
LIBRARY
（图书室）
A new issue!
有新书！
My name is Himiko Agari.
我的名字叫上理卑美子
I'm a very nervous person.
我非常容易紧张
If people look at me,
只要有人看着我
I just stop functioning.
就会紧张得手足无措 无法好好做事
And right now…
偏偏现在我…
I'm being watched by my classmate, Komi.
正受到同班的古见同学的监视
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind,
不过需要注意的是
they only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
MISSION 05 "IT'S JUST STAGE FRIGHT."
（任务05 会紧张怯场）
Komi is beautiful, smart, and popular.
说到古见同学 她是个美女 头脑聪明 广受众人欢迎
But she's down to earth.
但她不会因此盛气凌人
She's always so dignified.
总是表现得落落大方
She's brooding, reserved, and cool.
沉默寡言、帅气又有型
The more I think about her, the more I admire her!
越想就越觉得她很棒！
Me?
至于我…
My eyes are bad, and I'm not cute or anything.
视力不好 长得也没特别可爱
I'm chubby, my legs are short, and I get stage fright easily.
胖胖的 腿又短 而且容易紧张怯场
Komi… why are you looking at me?
古见同学她为什么要盯着我看？
I-I'm scared!
好可怕！
DID I DO SOMETHING?
（我做错了什么吗？）
My stomach hurts!
害我肚子开始痛了！
SINK
（蹲下）
I can relax in the restroom.
厕所真是个令人安心的地方
It's my own personal space.
这是专属于我的私人空间
Nobody can see me. Nobody is thinking about me.
没有人会看到我 也不会有人注意到我的存在
I love the restroom.
我好喜欢厕所啊
I could spend my life here.
我一辈子待在厕所里也没关系
Someone's there!
有人！
CAME TO ASK "ARE YOU OKAY?" (BUT CAN'T)
（是来问她要不要紧 但说不出口）
Sorry!
对不起！
I don't remember what I did, but I'm sorry!
我不记得做了什么事 但对不起！
Please! I'll do anything!
求求你！要我做什么都可以！
Forgive me! God! Buddha! Komi!
请原谅我吧！ 神啊！佛祖！古见大人！
SHUFFLE
（悄声离去）
My prayers were answered!
神明听到我的祷告了！
Now's my chance.
趁现在…
Oh, Agari!
喔 上理！
Perfect timing.
正好
Uh, um, yes? W-W-What can I foo for you?
请问有什摸事吗？
Ah! I was so nervous I messed up!
糟糕！太紧张 结巴了！
Sixth period gym class.
第六节体育课
It's in the gymnasium, not outside.
不去操场 改在体育馆上
Tell the class for me.
你去跟班上同学说
Uh, but… I… Um… Ah!
可…可是我…
I've got to get away!
我得快逃！
Yes! Of course!
好！我知道了！
Oh! Good answer.
嗯 回答得很有精神！
Now what should I do?
怎么办啊？
I've got to do it.
老师交代我做事
RESPONSIBILITY
（责任）
But my stomach hurts…
胃痛、肚子痛
It's alright! You've got this, Himiko Agari!
别担心 没事的 上理卑美子！
Ah!
啊！
Calm down! Just say this, loud and clear…
冷静下来 大声说…
"Sixth period gym is in the gymnasium."
“第六节体育课改在体育馆上”
Right? It's easy!
很简单吧？
Don't be afraid. Just speak clearly.
不要胆怯 清楚地说出来
Yes. In a loud voice, so I don't have to repeat myself.
没错 我要大声说出来 免得别人听不清楚还要再说一遍
Pa!
啪！
Pa?
啪？
What?! What is "Pa"?!
什么？“啪”是什么东西？
Why did I say that?
我怎么会发出这种声音？
-Everyone's looking! I'm so embarrassed! -You okay?
-大家都在看我 好丢脸！ -你没事吧？
What?
怎么回事？
I wish I could just disappe…
我好想从这个世界消失…
SHOCK
（吓到）
Sixth period gym is in the gymnasium!
第六节体育课改在体育馆上！
-HUH?! -BOW!
什么？
Wow! I can't believe it!
不会吧！
I…
我竟然…
I said it!
成功说出来了！
EUPHORIA
（开心）
HUBBUB
（窃窃私语）
What happened?
她发生什么事了？
Rewind the story by 20 minutes.
回溯到20分钟前
And anyway,
总之我想说的就是
I wanted to say I can't be friends with just anyone.
和任何人都成为朋友是不可能的
Komi must have preferences too, right?
古见同学应该也有 合得来和合不来的对象吧？
What are you on about, Najimi?
驯染 突然说这个干吗？
From all of my childhood friends,
我从儿时玩伴 也就是全校学生里
I've picked the people with the closest personalities to Komi!
选出了个性 跟古见同学比较相近的人！
Let's get her next friend from this list!
下一个朋友候补就从这里面挑吧！
What?? I love it.
什么？好帅喔！
First off.
先看第一号人选
Same class. Himiko Agari.
同班的上理卑美子
Oh, she was nervous during self-introductions.
喔 我记得她自我介绍时很紧张
Yeah.
没错
Agari is a good kid.
上理她是个好孩子
But she gets stressed around people.
但是很不擅长 面对人际关系带来的压力
Specifically, she goes red just from being looked at.
具体来说 光是被人盯着看
She cramps, hyperventilates, gets tongue-tied,
就会让她出现脸红、抽搐、呼吸急促
sweats a lot and her stomach starts to hurt.
口齿不清、流油汗、肚子痛等症状
Poor kid.
好可怜
KOMI FEELS A KINSHIP.
（很有亲近感）
Huh? Komi?
古见同学？
Wanna hear about number two?
那我们再去看第二号人选
Ah.
好
What happened to Komi?
奇怪 古见同学呢？
Agari's gone too.
什么？连上理都不见了
KOMI CAME TO SAY HELLO, BUT NOTHING CAME OUT.
（古见同学跟过来了 却紧张得说不出话来）
THE PRESENT
（现在）
I see. And in the end you couldn't talk to Agari.
原来如此 所以你最后 还是没能跟上理同学说上话
SHE WROTE IT ALL DOWN.
（请她把事情经过写在纸上）
GLOOM
（情绪低落）
It's alright! You'll have another chance.
放心 还有机会！
-Uh, um. -Ah!
-请问一下！ -喔
Komi, uh.
古见同学 那个…
You kept staring at me.
你今天一直盯着我看
And, uh.
那个…
It was really scary!
我真的很害怕！
SHOCK
（大受打击）
IT WAS SCARY!
（我真的很害怕！）
But…
可是…
I don't know why you were looking at me.
虽然不知道你为什么要盯着我看
Thanks to you, I…
多亏了你
was able to change a little!
我现在有点不一样了
So I wanted to say thank you!
所以我想跟你说谢谢！
Now's my chance!
就是现在！
Um, you two seem like you'd get along.
你们两位感觉很合得来呢
What if you became friends?
要不要交个朋友啊？
Huh? That's i-i-impossible!
什么？不可能的！
Nonononononono!
不可能！
Uh, no, I mean…
啊 我不是那个意思！
I'm not worthy enough to be Komi's friend.
我是觉得我实在配不上古见同学！
But…
可是…
PANT
（喘气）
If you want me to be your dog, I'll do my best!
如果是当古见同学的狗 我会努力胜任的！
Please treat me well!
还请多多指教！
Komi got another friend.
古见同学又多了一个朋友
BEFORE CLASS
（开始上课前）
TA-DA
（秀出来）
MISSION 06 "IT'S JUST A CELL PHONE."
（任务06 手机）
What's up?
怎么了吗？
BEEP
（哔哔声）
NOT BOTHERED BY HER PACE ANYMORE
（已经见怪不怪）
TAPPED THE WRONG KEY AND ERASED EVERYTHING
（按错 删除键按太久 全部都不见了）
BEGINNING TO GET BOTHERED
（开始动摇）
MY PARENTS BOUGHT ME A PHONE.
（我爸妈终于买手机给我了）
A flip phone? In this age??
现在才开始用翻盖式手机吗？
So, you've never had a phone until now?
这么说来 你原来至今都没用过手机啊？
I NEVER NEEDED ONE BEFORE.
（因为之前都没有必要）
That's really sad, Komi.
感觉好心酸啊 古见同学！
BUT
（可是）
NOW I NEED ONE.
（可是我现在需要）
THANKS TO YOU, I MADE LOTS OF FRIENDS.
（因为多亏了只野同学 我交到了好多朋友）
Komi!
古见同学！
ABOUT TO CRY
（快哭出来了）
AND SO, UM…
（所以那个…）
GLANCE
（偷瞥）
I NEED MY FRIENDS' NUMBERS.
（我想要朋友的电话号码）
I see.
我懂了
Why did she hesitate?
可是她为什么迟疑了一下？
Okay, let's go ask Najimi and Agari.
那我们一起去找驯染 和上理同学 跟他们要电话号码
She's pausing more than usual.
今天她比平时停顿得更久呢
I RELY ON YOU TOO MUCH. I'LL MANAGE.
（我之前太依赖你了 我会想办法跟他们要 我会努力）
Komi!
古见同学！
You've grown so quickly.
你什么时候成长了这么多？
FATHERLY PRIDE
（父亲的心情）
Oh! Morning Komi!
喔 古见同学 早安！
What's up?
怎么了吗？
TREMBLE
（颤抖）
What?
你要干吗？
Why is Komi pointing a flip phone at me?
你干吗用那个翻盖式手机对着我？
Tadano! Translate!
只野同学 快点翻译！
Sorry Najimi, I can only watch.
抱歉 驯染 我只能在一旁默默守望
Paper.
纸？
Phone.
手机？
Date… numbers?
日期…数字？
You want my phone number?
难道你是想知道我的手机号码？
NOD
（点头）
Yes! Alright!
太好了 成功了！
I could just enter it, instead of writing it down.
那就不用写在纸上 我直接用你的手机输入…
Ah!
啊！
I see. Alright.
我懂了 原来如此啊
Tadano's pretty thick for such a perceptive guy.
只野同学明明很会察言观色 有时却实在迟钝
Dumbass.
因为他是个笨蛋
Why are they talking about me?
什么？为什么会讲到我？
AGARI'S SEAT
（上理同学的座位）
Oh, K-K-Komi.
啊 古见同学！
Good morning!
早安！
Need a massage? Shall I buy you a drink?
要我帮你按摩肩膀吗？ 要我去帮你买饮料吗？
-Want me to lick your shoes? -Ew.
-要我舔你的鞋吗？ -什么？
Do you want to take a slutty picture of me and use it for your wallpaper?
天啊！莫非要把我的 丑态拍下来当作你的壁纸吗？
I'm so happy.
我太开心了
She gave up.
她决定放弃
You did well, Komi.
古见同学 你很努力呢！
You got Najimi's number anyway.
而且也拿到驯染的手机号码了
SHOW…
（展示）
Huh?
什么？
I'm sorry!
对不起！
You wanted my phone number, didn't you?
古见同学是想要我的手机号码吧？
I misunderstood.
我刚才误会了！
Of course, if you're going to call your dog, you need a phone.
也对 要叫狗来的时候 有电话号码比较方便！
Huh?
什么？
Also…
而且…
Komi wants to put Tadano's number in first.
古见同学第一个 想输入的是只野同学的号码
So write your number on a piece of paper.
所以你就写在纸上交给她吧
That's what Najimi told me.
驯染是这么跟我说的
I've got bad timing.
我好像挑错时机了
I-Is that true?
是这样吗？
NOD
（点头）
W-Well then…
那我就…
BEEP
（哔哔声）
Here you go.
拿去吧
CAN'T MAKE EYE CONTACT
（无法正视对方）
001 - HITOHITO TADANO
（电话簿 001 只野仁人）
Uh.
呃
Tadano screamed inside his heart.
只野同学在内心呐喊
HOMEROOM
（班会时间）
MISSION 07 "IT'S JUST A STUDENT ELECTION."
（任务07 要决定班级干部）
We're choosing class committees.
要来选班级干部了
First, class president.
好 首先来选班长
The top of our class.
也就是本班的头头
Does anyone want to do it?
有没有人自告奋勇？
SILENCE
（静悄悄）
What a bunch of slackers!
怎么一点干劲都没有？
Okay, nominations?
那就用推荐的
EVERYONE'S GAZE
（全班的视线）
KOMI
（古见）
No other nominations?
没有其他推荐人选吗？
I don't see any.
看来是没有
Alright, Komi. You want to do it?
那么古见 可以吗？
-Huh? -What?
-什么？ -怎么了？
SHIVER
（颤抖）
Trembling with excitement, I see.
看你都兴奋得发抖了
You're clearly very motivated!
古见干劲十足呢！
IMPOSSIBLE.
（认为绝对做不到）
HELP ME…
（救命啊）
Komi's biggest crisis yet.
古见同学遭遇世纪大危机
Hmm.
呃
The only option is to nominate myself…
没办法 我只好自告奋勇…
RAISE
（举手）
I oppose Komi for class president.
我反对由古见同学担任班长
Najimi?
驯染？
I'll take care of this.
交给我吧
Najimi's a hero!
驯染同学！
Huh? What are you saying, Najimi?
什么？驯染 你在说什么？
Oppose, huh?
你想造反吗？
-We're old friends but I won't hold back. -What's your reason?
-就算是儿时玩伴 我也饶不了你 -给我解释理由！
Najimi! I can't believe it!
驯染！你该不会…
You sacrificed yourself to save Komi?
打算牺牲自己来拯救古见同学？
-Think about it, guys. -Huh?
-你们仔细想想 -什么？
Komi's greatness can't be contained within the small role of class president.
古见同学她是当区区班长的人才吗？
You have a point!
有道理！
Huh?
什么？
I demand a higher rank for Komi!
所以我要求让她担任更高的职位！
-Totally. -Yeah.
-的确 -嗯
I agree with Najimi.
驯染说得没错！
Let's all decide Komi's position!
大家一起来决定古见同学的职位吧！
Yay!
哇！
GENERAL, EMPEROR, BOSS, CEO, SHE WHO MUSTN'T BE NAMED
（将军、陛下、老大、执行长 那个不能说出名字的人）
Alright.
好了
Komi's student council position is "God" then.
投票结果古见的职位就是“神”
GOD
（颤抖）
Ko-mi! G-od!
古见！神！
The position of class president is open.
现在班长位置空出来了
No nominations or volunteers?
有没有人自愿或推荐？
Tadano will do.
就让只野来当吧
We have our god, so it doesn't matter.
反正上面还有个神 他就不算头头
-I second Tadano. -Might as well have Tadano.
-就选只野 -好麻烦 就选只野吧
Work hard for our god, Tadano.
只野同学 好好为古见大人工作吧
Alright, class president is Tadano.
那么班长就决定是只野了
I got forced into it.
被迫当选了
TADANO WANTED TO BE ON AN ORDINARY COMMITTEE.
（我只想当不起眼的班级干部！）
MISSION 08 "IT'S JUST AN ACCIDENTAL CALL."
（任务08 打错电话）
CELL PHONE (FLIP-TYPE)
（翻盖式手机）
TRILL
（铃铃声）
BEEP
（哔哔声）
NOT MUCH TO DO BUT LISTEN TO RINGTONES
（没事可做 只能听来电铃声）
NOT MUCH TO DO BUT LOOK AT CONTACTS (SIX INCLUDING FAMILY)
（没事可做 只能浏览通讯录 加上家人总共六位）
KOMI PRETENDS TO MAKE A CALL
（古见同学假装在打电话）
RING
（拨号声）
HANDY! CALL JUST BY PUTTING IT TO YOUR EAR.
（很方便！具贴近耳朵 就能拨打电话的功能）
CLICK…
（接通）
H-Hello?
喂？
KOMI HANGS UP.
（古见同学挂断电话）
PANIC
（惊慌失措）
TRILL
（来电铃声）
CLICK
（接通）
Hello? Komi?
喂？是古见同学吗？
Um, I think you may have dialed the wrong number by accident,
我猜你刚刚应该是打错电话了
but just in case there's something wrong, I tried calling back.
但又担心你真的出事 所以现在才回拨给你
If you're okay, just say "Ah" or something.
如果没事的话 你出个声就行 只说“啊”也好
Um.
喔
The number you have dialed
您现在拨打的电话
i-i-is not in service.
目前无人使用
Komi?
古见同学？
I'm sorry. It was the wrong number.
对不起 刚才打错电话了
Oh.
这样啊
Sounds like she can talk a bit if it's over the phone.
通过电话的话 古见同学能稍微讲些话呢
Goodbye.
那我要挂了
Oh, uh. Okay.
喔 好
Her voice is so pretty!
她的声音超好听的！
Knock it off, Hitohito!
哥 吵死了！
KOMI'S HOUSE
（古见同学家）
HAPPY YET MORTIFIED OVER HER FIRST CALL
（第一次打电话 又羞又喜 非常兴奋）
Knock it off, Shoko.
姐 吵死了
HITOHITO TADANO
（通话记录 只野仁人）
MISSION 09 "IT'S JUST A GAME."
（任务09 斋藤先生游戏）
Starting with Ren, match the rhythm!
从恋字开始 配合节奏接下去
Oni, three!
鬼 三！
Pe, pe, pe!
呸、呸、呸！
Osa, one!
长 一！
Pe!
呸！
Saito!
斋藤先生！
I'm Saito!
我是斋藤！
AH HA HA HA
（大笑）
GLOOM
（隆隆声）
WANTS TO TRY
（想玩玩看）
Um… Do you want to try it?
那个 你想玩玩看吗？
NOD
（点头）
She's doing so well.
这是好现象！
But it's the cool kids.
可是那团体的都是班上很潮的同学
It won't be easy to join in.
要加入是非常困难的
I'm sure Komi realizes that.
古见同学应该也很清楚这一点
After school, when everyone's gone,
那等放学后大家都不在了
we can invite Najimi and Agari and have a private game.
我们再找驯染和上理同学 偷偷来玩
TEAM NO PEOPLE SKILLS
（无社交能力组）
I can hear you, Tadano!
我听到了 只野同学！
Hey, Komi! Do you want to join in?
什么？古见同学想加入我们吗？
It's fine! Come on over!
可以啊 快过来！
No way! Is Komi joining us?
天啊 古见同学要加入吗？
Oops.
什么？
Oh no, my face is breaking out today.
不要啦 人家今天皮肤状态不好
It's okay. Everyone's happy to have you. Right?
放心啦 大家都很开心啊 对吧？
Her Majesty? Here?
古见大人要来这边吗？
-A manifestation of a god? -We are blessed.
-神明要显灵了吗？ -感谢神明
Though it's not a typical display of happiness.
虽然开心的方式有点不寻常
Uh… Ah! Huh?
呃 啊？
Heh-heh.
嘿嘿
She needs a little tough love in order to build her people skills.
要锻炼社交能力 就得像这样下猛药啊 只野同学
Are you just going to watch?
你只会在一旁看着吗？
Watch Komi get bullied?
看着古见同学遭人戏弄！
Damn it! I guess I've gotta try!
这小子！只好硬着头皮上了！
Um, can I join too?
请问一下 也可以让我加入吗？
Of course. The more the merrier.
当然可以啊 人多比较好玩嘛
-Are you joining us too? -Ahaha, yay!
-怎么了？只野同学也要加入吗？ -太好了！
Join us.
加入吧
Huh? Who does he think he is?
什么？这小子以为他是谁？
I'll be nice for Her Majesty, but seriously, beat it, trash.
在古见大人面前不能说狠话 但真心希望他快滚 人渣！
-Read the room. -Ahaha, go away.
-都不会察言观色吗？ -碍事
Begone.
回去吧
I can practically hear what they're thinking.
我几乎可以听到大家的心声
The Saito Game is kind of hard.
斋藤先生游戏难度有点高
So let's start with Yubisuma.
先来玩“翘翘拇指”吧
Hold out your fists and say a number in turn.
“翘翘拇指”就是由玩家翘拇指 并依序喊出数字的一种游戏
If the thumb count matches your number, remove a fist and continue.
若喊的数字和拇指 数目一致就放下一只手
You win once both are gone. Easy, right?
谁两手先放下谁就赢 很简单吧？
I'll start.
那就从我开始
Yubisuma, six.
翘翘拇指 六！
One too few.
少一只
Twinkle, nine.
啦啦 九！
Oh, yay!
啊 太好了！
Huh?
什么？
Ready, set, four!
预备起 四！
Oh no.
没说中
Huh?
什么？
-Chichichichi barichichi, 10! -Hang on a second!
-起起起起吧哩起起 十！ -等一下！
The game has many local variations.
每个地区的说法都不一样
In the end, everyone did it their own way.
结果就让大家各喊各的
Is this really okay?
这样好吗？
Yay!
太好了！
KOMI'S TURN
（轮到古见同学）
Five.
五
SLICK…
（竖起）
They let her win!
大家故意让她赢！
KOMI WON! TADANO GOT LAST PLACE.
（古见同学赢了 只野同学是最后一名）
Heh.
嘻嘻
Looks like she got the hang of it.
好像越来越进入状况了嘛
Let's up the stakes.
那接下来输的人要受罚
Let's play Bamboo Shoot!
来玩“竹笋长高高”！
The loser has to make a kissy face!
输的人必须做出亲嘴的表情！ 你们觉得怎么样啊？
A kissy face?!
亲嘴的表情？
I want to see Komi's kissy face!
想看！好想看古见同学亲嘴的表情！
Bamboo Shoot is…
“竹笋长高高”就是…
a game of speed with yelling and arm raising.
玩家喊“长高高”的同时要举起双手
Everyone counts in sequential order.
这游戏比的是速度 也要讲举手顺序的数字
Say the wrong number and you lose!
如果数字和别人一样 或始终没举手的人都算输
It's a thinking game! Try it at home!
是预测对手行动的脑力游戏 大家也来试试看！
I've got to win!
我要赢 我一定要赢！
A kiss? A kissy face to me?
亲嘴？对我做出亲嘴的表情？
The mood has changed!
跟刚才的气势完全不同！
Let's begin.
那就开始了
Bamboo, bamboo…
竹笋
Shoot! One shoot!
长高高！一长高高！
WATCHING A RIDICULOUS SCENE
（看着笨蛋的眼神）
EVERYONE LOST
（结果每个人都输了）
Okay, once more.
那就再来一次
Bamboo, bamboo. Shoot!
竹笋 长高高！
-One shoot! -Cheater!
-一长高高！ -好卑鄙！
-Two shoot! -Three shoot!
-二长高高！ -三长高高！
-Four shoot! -Five shoot!
-四长高高！ -五长高高！
They're like a well-oiled machine!
糟糕 主控权完全在他们手上！
They're aiming to see Komi's kissy face!
他们是真心想看 古见同学亲嘴的表情！
You two are the only ones left.
剩下的只有你们两个了
They've trapped me!
被逼到绝境了！
Win, Tadano, win!
赢吧 只野 赢吧！
Augh!
呃！
If I win, we'll get to see Komi's kissy face.
我赢了就能看到 古见同学亲嘴的表情了！
No!
不行！
I can't put Komi through such trauma!
我不能让古见同学留下心理阴影！
Komi! You've gotta say it!
古见同学 快说啊！
Seven shoot!
快说“七长高高”！
DOESN'T GET THE RULES
（搞不太懂游戏规则）
Oh no…
没救了
-Is there some other way I could lose? -Win already!
-有其他让我输掉的方法吗？ -快赢啊！
I've got an idea.
我想到了一个方法
I'd rather not, but I have no choice.
可是…算了 我豁出去了
E-Eight shoot.
八长高高
Oh no! I said the wrong number!
糟糕 我喊错数字了！
I guess I lost!
是我输了！
Kill me now.
好想死！
Class is starting.
要上课了
Sorry Komi.
抱歉 古见同学
Let's play the Saito Game next time.
下次再来玩斋藤先生游戏吧
THE TWO RETURNED TO THEIR SEATS.
（两人回到座位上）
ARE YOU OKAY?
（你还好吗？）
Ah.
啊
Uh, yeah. I'm fine.
我没事
I just feel like I have a stomach ulcer.
只是快要胃穿孔了
Ow, ouchie…
好痛
Oh it hurts…
痛死了
Huh?
什么？
THANK YOU. I HAD FUN.
（谢谢你 我玩得很开心）
Oh.
啊
Oh good.
嗯 那就好
Tadano. Show me your kissy face later!
只野同学 待会要做亲嘴的表情喔！
Ow, ow, ow.
好痛
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：蒋文昊